Finding aid for the Betty Millard papers SSC.MS.00673
Sophia Smith Collection
Betty Millard papers
1911-2010
Sophia Smith Collection
Millard, Betty
SSC.MS.00673
35.542 linear feet (69 boxes)
Betty Millard was a writer, political and labor activist, and photographer. She was involved in Communism and Marxism and was interested in global social justice. Millard was the author of Woman Against Myth, a key feminist seminal that examined the history of the women's movement in the United States, in the socialist movement, and in the USSR. The papers document Millard's personal and professional life. It includes writings and photos by, about, and collected by Millard, paper records of Millard's travels, and personal journals from the entirety of her life, some which document her personal exploration of, and struggle with, her sexuality.
Biographical Note
Elizabeth (Betty) Boynton Millard was born on October 12, 1911. She was born to a wealthy, conservative family in Highland Park, Illinois and lived there until she attended college. Her mother, Elizabeth (Bessie) Bell Boynton (1882-1980) was a Smith College student from 1900-1902 and studied painting, sculpture, and music. She became an artist. Her father, Everett Lee Millard (1877-1933) was an attorney. Betty was the second of four children; younger to Everett Lee (Chevy) Millard, Jr. (1909-2000); older to Malcolm (Mac) S. Millard (1914-1999), and Graham Millard (1921-1921). Malcolm's first wife, Margaret Wentworth Owings, whose work focused on endangered species conservation, was a life-long friend to Betty Millard. Betty Millard remained close to her brother Malcolm throughout her life, despite their significant political and lifestyle differences. Her closest familial relationship for the latter half of her life was with her niece Olivia Millard, with whom she shared a love of nature, travel and conservation.
Millard first attended the University of Chicago from 1930-1932, but transferred to Barnard College in 1932. She briefly studied at the University of London and in Vienna during her college years. Her interest in political activism and social justice flourished during this time period and directed her professional interests for the continuation of her life. Millard was drawn to the on-campus activism at Barnard College, and marched against the U.S. government's support of Francisco Franco in the Spanish Civil War. She graduated from Barnard College in 1934 and enrolled at Columbia Law School, but left after one year in order to pursue her activism. In exploring her preferred ideals of equality and fairness, Betty joined the Young Communist League in 1936 and the Communist party in 1940. In 1935, she moved to Greenwich Village, where she was based for the rest of her life.
From 1943-1947, Betty Millard worked as an editor and writer at The New Masses, a publication focused on American Marxism. In 1947, during her time at The New Masses, Betty wrote the widely acclaimed, key feminist seminal, Woman Against Myth. It was published as a 24-page pamphlet in 1948 distributed with the magazine and was released by International later that year.Woman Against Myth examined the history of the women's movement in the United States, in the socialist movement, and in the USSR.
From 1949-1951, Betty Millard worked in Paris, France and Berlin, Germany as the American Secretary in the directorate of the Women's International Democratic Federation (WIDF). The WIDF was a post-war, radical feminist organization that aligned with the global Communist movement. Millard was also active in the Congress of American Women (CAW), an affiliate of WIDF. Her work for both organizations took her to France, Italy, the Soviet Union, Poland, Hungary, China, Finland, Denmark, Switzerland, and Germany. When she returned to the United States in 1951, her passport was lifted due to suspected Communist affiliation.
From 1951-1956, Betty Millard worked as an editor and writer at the magazine Latin America Today, reporting on the political and social developments south of the United States border. In April 1959, Millard was subpoenaed to testify as a hostile witness before the House of Un-American Activities Committee during the McCarthy trials. The House was investigating the Congress of American Women, Millard's work for them, as well as her personal political views. Millard left the Communist Party in the late 1950's – possibly as a result of the Khrushchev revelations, or possibly out of dissatisfaction with the Party's hostile viewpoints on feminism, women's rights and gay rights.
In 1960, Millard developed a passion for photography and installed a darkroom on the top floor of her Greenwich Village brownstone. Millard studied photography with Paul Caponigro, Lisa Modell, and Ansel Adams. She was interested in photography of nature, political struggles, and portraiture. Millard created "picture stories" while travelling including on trips up the Essequibo and Pomeroon Rivers in then-British Guiana; visiting the artist, David Alfaro Siqueiros, at work in his studio; and to Chile in 1970 to photograph Chilean mural art.
Betty Millard spent the remainder of her life travelling to various parts of the world, often in service of advocacy. Betty Millard supported many activist organizations, especially in Latin America. She worked on campaigns such as organizing a committee to free the Mexican muralist, David Siqueiros, from prison, movements that were against the Vietnam War, environmentalism, and later in her life, she joined the fight for lesbian and gay rights. Millard was also a philanthropist and supported various activist groups, including the North Star Fund, which worked to create a more equitable and democratic city for all New Yorkers. She attended the March on Washington in 1963.
Millard met, interviewed, and befriended a variety of political figures throughout her life including artists David Siqueiros and Diego Rivera, W. E. B. Du Bois, Ho Chi Minh, Zhou Enlai, Fidel Castro, Marie-Claude Vaillant-Couturier, Cheddi and Janet Jagan, Paul and Eslanda Robeson, Elizabeth Moos, and Bella Abzug. Millard and Janet Jagan met while they both attended the University of Chicago. Millard would continue to be close friends with the Jagans for the remainder of their lives.
Millard traveled through British Guiana with politician Cheddi Jagan as he campaigned for Chief Minister, and later, Premier. She spoke alongside Jagan at an event in New York City shortly after he was elected President of independent Guyana on December 5, 1992. In this, her last public speaking appearance, she eloquently compared Jagan's early campaign-trail appeal to that of the recently-elected U.S. President, Bill Clinton.
Despite privately writing about her struggles with her sexual orientation in journals, Millard did not come out as gay until her late 80s except to close family and friends. Millard often referenced her crushes on schoolmates in her journals and described her younger self as bisexual. Due to the social implications of being gay and the explicit homophobia of the Communist Party, Millard took measures to reject this part of her life by seeking conversion therapy from 1942-1948; she was hospitalized in 1956 for a breakdown related to her struggles with her sexuality. Despite this, Millard had several important long-term relationships with women prior to, and after, coming out.
Millard enjoyed writing short stories and poetry, most of which were autobiographical. Some of Millard's writing was anthologized, and others can be found in The Guardian. In 1960, Millard purchased a small farm in Dutchess County, upstate New York and regularly spent time there.
Millard passed away on March 6, 2010 at her home in New York City, New York.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Betty Millard papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by her estate executors - her niece, Olivia Millard, and her close friend, Lisa Springer, in two accessions in 2011 and 2013.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following collections at Smith College Special Collections:
MS 452, Communism, Socialism, and Left-Wing Politics Collection
MS 594, Women's International Democratic Federation (WIDF) Records
MS 482, Miscellaneous Organizations Collection
Additional WIDF materials can be found in the Sophia Smith Collection in the papers of
MS 300, Mary Metlay Kaufman
MS 85, Dorothy Kenyon
MS 165, Mary van Kleeck
MS 175, Ruth Frances Woodsmall
WIDF's magazine Women of the Whole World is located with the MS 537,Sophia Smith Collection Periodicals Collection
Betty Millard's mother, Elizabeth (Bessie) Bell Boynton (1882-1980) was a Smith College student from 1900-1902 and studied painting, sculpture, and music. Materials can be found within the Smith College Archives.
The Margaret Owings Collection resides at the Bancroft Library.
Scope and Contents
The Betty Millard papers span the period of 1884-2011 and relate to both her personal and professional life. The bulk of the papers span 1915-2011. The major topic of the papers revolve around Millard's professional life and her personal writings. The collection includes clippings, articles, correspondence, personal and collected writings, and photography.
Arrangement
The materials are organized into five series:
Biographical
Correspondence
Professional
Writings
Photographs
The Photographs Series is organized into four sub-series:
Negatives
Slides
Prints
Photograms
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital reproductions of the audiovisual materials in this collection. Access to audiovisual materials requires the creation of digital access copies. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request digitization of and access to materials.
Millard, Betty; Jagan, Cheddi; Jagan, Janet; Vaillant-Courturier, Marie-Claude; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Siqueiros, David Alfaro; Castro, Fidel, 1926-2016; Levit, Herschel; Communists--Biography; Women communists; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities; Congress of American Women; Women and peace; Women's International Democratic Federation; Women journalists--United States--Biography; Latin America--Description and travel; Lesbian activists; Millard, Olivia; Millard, Olivia
- Biographical materials, circa 1884-2010; 1; 5.3 linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  The Biographical Materials series contains biographical information about Millard's personal life. It includes address books, biographies/autobiographies, clippings, journals, memorabilia, and information about her early childhood years and education. The journals are from early to late in her life, are very detailed, and include information on her education (with sketches and class notes), travelling (with maps, journaling, and notes), personal journals, and journals on her gardening (with maps, sketches, and notes). Memorabilia includes United Nations membership cards, passports, and collected buttons. Autobiographies include detailed lists of trips with friends, companions, and various jobs she had.
  - Address books, circa 2003 (Box 1)
  - Articles and clippings, circa 1921-1999 (Box 1)
  - Autobiographies, 1963-2010 (Box 1)
  - Biographies, 1997-2012 (Box 1)
  - Calendars, 1930-2010 (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Financial records, 1978-1999 (Box 2)
  - Journals, 1925-1996 (Box 2, Box 3)
  - Journals: Garden journal, 1967-1987 (Box 3)
  - Journals: Travel notebooks, 1949-1998; 19 folders (Box 3, Box 4)
  - Memorabilia: Buttons, circa 1919-1984; 1-4 folders (Box 4, Box 5, Box 6)
  - Memorabilia: Hair, 1911-1951; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - Memorabilia: Lightbox, Undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - Memorabilia: Matchbooks, Undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
  - Memorabilia: Stamps, Undated; 1 folders (Box 6, Box 9)
  - Memorabilia: Korea purse, Undated; 1 boxes (Box 7)
  - Memorabilia: Blank travel postcards, Undated; 1 boxes (Box 8)
  - Memorabilia: Sketches, Undated; 1 folders (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous: Jobs and photography, Circa 1966-1970 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1930-1969 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous: Receipts, 1884-1889 (Box 9)
  - Notes: Elizabeth Moos, 1984-1985 (Box 9)
  - Notes: General, circa 1945-2003 (Box 9)
  - Notes: Office, circa 1954-1957 (Box 9)
  - Notes: Writing and obituaries, circa 1997-1999 (Box 9)
  - Personal: Birth certificate, 1911 (Box 9)
  - Personal: Passports, 1931-1995 (Box 9)
  - Personal: Passport paperwork, 1958 (Box 9)
  - Personal, 1896-1953 (Box 9)
  - Personal: Camp Quinibeck, 1925-1930 (Box 10)
  - Travel, 1949-1994 (Box 10)
  - Educational, circa 1918-1942 (Box 11, Box 12, Box 13)
- Correspondence, circa 1918-2010; 2; 3.13 linear feet
  The Correspondence series is arranged first by subject and then chronologically. Some notable correspondents include Cheddi and Janet Jagan, Marie-Claude Vaillant-Couturier, and W.E.B. Du Bois. There is correspondence from her time at the organizations she worked at. Much of the chronological correspondence contains letters between Millard and her family members. Millard's original subpoena from Congress to testify to the Committee on Un-American Activities on April 21, 1959 is included in the 1951-1959 correspondence.
  - Holiday Cards, 1955-2007 (Box 13, Box 14)
  - Letters to family, circa 1918-1982 (Box 15, Box 16)
  - Julia Allen, circa 2000-2003 (Box 16)
  - Carleton Banks, circa 1962-1988 (Box 16)
  - Personal correspondence and notes, 1958-2000 (Box 16)
  - Cheddi and Janet Jagan, 1956-1999 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1976-1996 (Box 17)
  - Marie-Claude Vaillant-Couturier, 1952-1992 (Box 17)
  - Gita Banerjea, 1950-1987 (Box 17)
  - W.E.B. Du Bois, 1955-1959 (Box 17)
  - Lloyd L. Brown, 1976-1997 (Box 17)
  - Earl Robinson, circa 1988-1990 (Box 17)
  - North Star Fund, circa 1974-1999 (Box 17)
  - Latin American Today, circa 1951-1966 (Box 17)
  - To Betty Millard at New Masses, 1945-1958 (Box 17)
  - Latin America correspondence, circa 1953-1954 (Box 17)
  - Latin American Research Bureau (LARB) activities, circa 1951-1956 (Box 18)
  - Regarding Betty Millard's writings, circa 1945-1948 (Box 18)
  - Chronological, 1931-1939 (Box 18)
  - Chronological, 1947-2008 (Box 19)
  - Chronological, 1953-2011 (Box 20)
  - Chronological, 1999-2008 (Box 21)
- Professional records, circa 1931-1996; 3; 2.96 linear feet
  The Professional Records series is organized into three categories: Administrative, Subjects, and Research. Notable folders include Millard's activist work in the Artists Committee for Siqueiros organization, research for her writings, transcript and notes from her interview with Diego Rivera, and copies of newsletters and pamphlets from various news outlets and organizations she worked for.
  - Administrative: Floppy disks, circa 1985-1997 (Box 22)
  - Administrative: MCM Art Prism, Undated (Box 22)
  - Administrative: Letterheads, Undated (Box 23)
  - Subjects: Artists Committee for Siqueiros, 1959-2001 (Box 23, Box 24, Box 25)
  - Subjects: Diego Rivera interview, circa 1954-1955; 7 folders (Box 24)
  - Subjects: Marie Claude Vaillant-Couturier, 1955-1996; 2 Cassettes (Box 25)
  - Subjects: Cheddi and Janet Jagan, circa 1977-1992; 1 folders (1-2) (Box 26)
  - Research (unknown), circa 1949-1951; 1 folders (3) (Box 26)
  - Research: American Women for Peace (AWP), circa 1949-1952; 1 folders (4) (Box 26)
  - Research: U.S. Institute on Women, 1949; 1 folders (5) (Box 26)
  - Research: Budapest, Second Women's International Congress, 1949; 1 folders (6) (Box 26)
  - Research: VI, Soviet Union (S.U.), undated; 1 folders (7) (Box 26)
  - Research: VII, Other Countries, undated; 1 folders (8) (Box 26)
  - Research: Around the world, circa 1948-1951; 1 folders (9) (Box 26)
  - Research: Miscellaneous-Women, circa 1948-1949; 1 folders (10) (Box 26)
  - Research: Congress of American Women (CAW)-Statue of Women Commission (St of W C), circa 1948; 1 folders (11) (Box 26)
  - Research: Congress of American Women (CAW)-General, circa 1946-1949; 1 folders (12) (Box 26)
  - Research: United Nations, circa 1949-1951; 1 folders (13) (Box 26)
  - Research: VIII, Women in Society, circa 1948; 1 folders (Box 26)
  - Research: IX, 1947-1948; 1 folders (Box 26)
  - Research: X, Women in Society, circa 1948; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research (unknown), circa 1947-1984; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research: Class, general, circa 1948; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research: II, Woman in Society, undated; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research: Old Congress of American Women (CAW) writing, 1970-1999; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research: Women, Wide - articles, etc. by Betty Millard, circa 1948-1951; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research: Charles St. for Peace Organizing, circa 1967-1968; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research: Organizing, circa 1931-1936; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research: FWI + FG, Fr. in Amer. - Gene, 1964-1966; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research: FWI + FG, FG, 1964; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research: Guyana, circa 1997-1998; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research: Millard's friends and interests, organizing, circa 1979-1990; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research: Employment, circa 1959-1961; 1 folders (Box 27)
  - Research: Latin American Facts, 1950-1952; 1 folders (Box 28)
  - Research: Latin America Today, 1953-1956; 1 folders (Box 28)
  - Research: Ideas for Latin America articles, 1957; 1 folders (Box 28)
  - Research: Latin America lists, 1955-1956; 1 folders (Box 28)
  - Research: Latin America testimonials, 1955-1956; 1 folders (Box 28)
- Writings, circa 1933-2000; 4; 4.84 linear feet
  The Writings series is organized into two categories: writings by Millard and writings collected by her. Millard's writings include drafts and final copies of her pamphlet Women Against Myth, released in 1948 while employed at the publication New Masses; Women On Guard, released in 1948, poetry, short stories, and fiction. Millard's collected writings include "people's" music scores and lyrics, Marxist periodicals and pamphlets on a variety of Marxist issues, materials on American race relations, feminist press materials, pamphlets and literature related to people's movements worldwide (China, Cuba, Guyana and the USSR are most heavily represented), and records from events such as Congressional hearings on communism.
  There is an incomplete list of slides, negatives, and collected writings and periodicals available.
  Separated Materials
  From the "Collected by" subseries in Series IV, removed duplicate materials, widely available materials not authored/obviously used by Millard and/or unrelated to collection scope.
  A list of removed materials is available on request.
  - Writing by Millard, 1933-1996; 3 boxes (Box 29, Box 30, Box 31)
  - Collected by Millard, 1935-2000; 9 boxes
    - Music (lyrics and songbooks), 1924-1998 (Box 32)
    - Autographed pamphlets/programs, 1952 (Box 33)
    - Marxist periodicals, 1938-1980 (Box 33)
    - General Marxism (pamphlets), 1935-1960 (Box 33, Box 34)
    - Marxism and gender (pamphlets), 1936-1976 (Box 34)
    - Feminist press (periodicals, pamphlets), 1974-1994 (Box 34)
    - Marxism and race (pamphlets), 1947-1965 (Box 34)
    - Race relations in the USA (books, pamphlets, poetry), 1938-1965 (Box 35)
    - Unions/labor organizing (pamphlets), 1936-1973 (Box 35)
    - China (communist pamphlets, woodcuts), 1949-1989 (Box 35, Box 36)
    - Cuba (communist pamphlets, poetry), 1963-1983 (Box 36)
    - France (Gabriel Péri, communist pamphlet), 1945-1946 (Box 37)
    - Germany (Rosa Luxemburg), 1972-1978 (Box 37)
    - Guyana/Guiana (revolutionary periodicals, pamphlets), 1963-2000 (Box 37)
    - Mexico (Diego Rivera plates, Siqueiros), 1967 (Box 37)
    - USSR (books, pamphlets, art), 1940-1969 (Box 38)
    - North Vietnam (pamphlet), 1971 (Box 38)
    - US Congress, Supreme Court records, 1956-1960 (Box 38)
    - Human rights/history, 1943-1969 (Box 38)
    - Subversive literature, 1951-1967 (Box 39)
    - Essays, 1981-1996 (Box 39)
    - Barnard Quarterly, 1933-1934 (Box 39)
    - Unidentified notes, scraps (Box 39)
    - Inscriptions photocopied from separated books (Box 39)
    - Magazines, posters, art books (Box 40)
- Photographs, circa 1924-2002; 5; 10.88 linear feet
  The Photography Materials series is arranged into four sub-series: Negatives, Slides, Photographs, and Photograms. The series includes photographs of Millard's travels, political activities, portraits of family and friends and landscapes, as well as her notes and captions.
  - Negatives, circa 1954-1966; 8 boxes
    The negatives sub-series contains negatives of Millard's travels, protests and peace marches, portraits of family, friends and colleagues, landscapes and art photography. Note that this series contains many of the same photos in the prints sub-series; researchers can use the roll number to match them. Negatives in this series are mainly in the format of slides and Bower files. This category also includes internegatives and notebooks with Millard's notes on rolls (see Box 47).
    - Roll 94 (Box 41)
    - Rolls 89-90, 101-130, 1964 (Box 41)
    - Rolls 51-81, 1963 (Box 41)
    - Rolls 20-50, 1954-1962 (Box 41)
    - Miscellaneous Latin America Research, 1953-1955 (Box 41)
    - Rolls 82-87, 91-100, 1964 (Box 41)
    - Rolls 132-181, 1964-1966 (Box 41)
    - Rolls 283-406 (Chile, Peru), 1970-1978 (Box 41)
    - Roll 33 (Box 41)
    - Rolls 407-517, 1979-1993 (Box 42)
    - Rolls 209-211 and Magazine Clippings (Box 42)
    - Other People's Negatives, 1961-1975 (Box 42)
    - Rolls 184-276 (Box 42)
    - Print (Roll 16) (Box 42)
    - Rolls 180-351 (Box 42)
    - Rolls 268-380, 1969-1978 (Box 42)
    - Rolls 262-377 (Box 43)
    - Bower File, Model 664, 1965-1969 (Box 43)
    - Man Hole Covers (Box 43)
    - Rolls 410-411, 1979 (Box 43)
    - Internegatives (Box 43)
    - Manhole Covers Rolls 387-420 (Box 43)
    - Bower Negative File Model 45 (Box 43)
    - Notebook Roll 13-50, 1961-1963 (Box 44)
    - Notebook Roll 51-141, 1963-1965 (Box 44)
    - Notebook Roll 142-320, 1965-1972 (Box 44)
    - Notebook Roll 322-447, 1972-1982 (Box 44)
    - Notebook Roll 450-517, 1982-1995 (Box 44)
    - Europe, 1930-1931 (Box 44)
    - Rolls 390-514 (Box 44, Box 45)
    - Rolls 120, 168, 172, 218 (Box 45)
    - Rolls 81-122 (Box 45)
    - Rolls 236, 238, 322, 383, 387 (Box 45)
    - Miscellaneous Negatives, 1954 (Box 45)
    - Italy and Paris, 1959 (Box 45)
    - USSR, 1959 (Box 45)
    - USSR, Color, 1959 (Box 45)
    - Paris, New York, 1959 (Box 45)
    - Cuba, Color, 1960 (Box 45)
    - Farm, Color, 1960 (Box 45)
    - Farm, Other Negatives, 1960-1961 (Box 45)
    - Roll 1 (Box 45)
    - Florence, Color, Roll 2 (Box 45)
    - Rome, Color, Roll 3 (Box 45)
    - Roll 4 (Box 45)
    - Roll 5 (Box 45)
    - Roll 6 (Box 45)
    - Roll 7, Color (Box 45)
    - Roll 8, Color (Box 45)
    - Ejido, Roll 10, 1961 (Box 45)
    - Women Strike for Peace (WSP) Demonstration, Roll 11 (Box 45)
    - Roll 12 (Box 45)
    - Roll 13 (Box 45)
    - Roll 14 (Box 45)
    - Roll 15 (Box 45)
    - Roll 16 (Box 45)
    - Roll 17 (Box 45)
    - Roll 18 (Box 45)
    - Roll 19 (Box 45)
    - Citron Interview, UN Demonstration, Roll 20, 1962 (Box 45)
    - Ejido, Roll 21, 1962 (Box 46)
    - Ejido, Roll 22, 1962 (Box 46)
    - Ejido, Roll 23, 1962 (Box 46)
    - Rolls 24-30 (Box 46)
    - Roll 31 (Box 46)
    - Peace Demonstration, Roll 32, 1962 (Box 46)
    - Rolls 33-38 (Box 46)
    - Roll 39 (Box 46)
    - Rolls 40-43 (Box 46)
    - Roll 44 (Box 46)
    - Roll 45 (Box 46)
    - Roll 48 (Box 46)
    - Roll 49 (Box 46)
    - Roll 50 (Box 46)
    - Roll 51 (Box 46)
    - Roll 52 (Box 46)
    - Roll 54 (Box 46)
    - Rolls 55-57 (Box 46)
    - Roll 58 (Box 46)
    - Roll 59 (Box 46)
    - Roll 60 (Box 46)
    - Roll 62 (Box 46)
    - Roll 63 (Box 46)